{
  "2025-12-05": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "and he that will not harden his heart, to him is given the greater portion of the word, until it is given unto him to know the mysteries of God until he know then in full.",
      "hint": "Alma 12:10",
      "cipher": "WSJXCAKUHNYQRPFZIBTMDEVGLO"
    },
    "wordle": "TARRY",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "D&C 137:7",
      "referenceText": "All who have died without a knoweldge of this gospel, who would have received it if they had been permitted to tarry, shall be heirs of the celestial kingdom of God.",
      "question": "What does it mean to have a knowledge of the gospel?",
      "response": "There are two senses in which we might have a knowledge of the gospel. The first sense is more of a box-ticking exercise that applies to things like the performance of ordinances and believing in the literal name of Christ. The second sense is more about the knowledge of the truth as we seek it, live it, and apply it. \n\n The Lord is saying here that the first sense doesn't matter all that much, and that even the second sense is mediated by the principle that where much is given, much is required."
    }
  },
  "2025-12-06": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "...And if their works were good in this life, and the desires of their hearts were good, that they should also, at the last day, be restored unto that which is good.",
      "hint": "Alma 41:3",
      "cipher": "YMGUSONVQIDHXLPWZTJFCKBRAE"
    },
    "wordle": "MATCH",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "D&C 137:9",
      "referenceText": "For I, the Lord, will judge all men according to their works, according to the desire of their hearts.",
      "question": "What do you want? \nFor yourself?\nFor your family?\nFor the world in general?\n\nHow well do your actions match up with those desires?",
      "response": ""
    }
  },
  "2025-12-07": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "for as the body without the spirit is dead, so faith without works is dead also.",
      "hint": "James 2:26",
      "cipher": "WOPHBUMAJVDQIKTSNXZYRFCLEG"
    },
    "wordle": "RENEW",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "D&C 138:50",
      "referenceText": "For the dead had looked upon the long absence of their spirits from their bodies as a bondage.",
      "question": "Why would the absence of a body be seen as a bondage?",
      "response": "Think about a thing that you WANT to do or be, but haven't yet been able to accomplish. Does that gap between wanting and being feel a bit like a bondage? I don't know what we'll experience in the spirit world, but in this life, until I can EMBODY the things that my spirit desires, I feel as though I am in bondage. \n\nRepentance and resurrection go hand in hand. We become reborn, with the ability to act in accordance with our best desires."
    }
  },
  "2025-12-09": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "For he will give unto the faithful line upon line, precept upon precept; and I will try you and prove you herewith. And whoso layeth down his life in my cause, for my name’s sake, shall find it again, even life eternal.",
      "hint": "D&C 98:12-13",
      "cipher": "IETLCNYDPAWKBJMGRXUFOSZVHQ"
    },
    "wordle": "FIRST",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Article of Faith #4",
      "referenceText": "We believe that the first principles and ordinances of the Gospel are: first, Faith in the Lord Jesus Christ; second, Repentance; third, Baptism by immersion for the remission of sins; fourth, Laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost.",
      "question": "Why do they come in this order? Do we only go through this cycle once? ",
      "response": "Every time we learn a new principle, whether or not it's obviously related to the gospel, we go through this process. \n\nWe learn what is good, we change our lives to conform to what is good, we commit to this new life, and continue to work for mastery of this new thing, or to \"catch the spirit\" of it. "
    }
  },
  "2025-12-10": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And are built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself being the chief corner stone; In whom all the building fitly framed together groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord:",
      "hint": "Ephesians 2:20-21",
      "cipher": "OSMTBZUJNGVRFADCHLYWXEIQPK"
    },
    "wordle": "CHART",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Article of Faith #6",
      "referenceText": "We believe in the same organization that existed in the Primitive Church, namely, apostles, prophets, pastors, teachers, evangelists, and so forth.",
      "question": "The offices listed here bear very little resemblence to the organization charts of the modern day church. What is this talking about?",
      "response": "Rather than focus on the names of the offices, focus on the jobs they carry out:\n\n Apostles bear witness of Christ and direct the church. Prophets are the Lord's mouthpiece. Pastors care for the spiritual and temporal needs of their local congregations. Teachers help us learn and understand the gospel, and Evangelists share the gospel with the world. \n\nEvery function is necessary, and has always been found in God's church, regardless of the actual title. "
    }
  },
  "2025-12-11": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "if it were possible that you could have just men to be your kings, who would establish the laws of god[...]if this could always be the case then it would be expedient that ye should always have kings to rule over you. ",
      "hint": "Mosiah 29:13",
      "cipher": "EQLNVWBDCZYJOIGMKTAHPXFURS"
    },
    "wordle": "RULER",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Articles of Faith #11 and 12",
      "referenceText": "We claim the privilege of worshiping Almighty God according to the dictates of our own conscience, and allow all men the same privilege, let them worship how, where, or what they may. \n\n We believe in being subject to kings, presidents, rulers, and magistrates, in obeying, honoring, and sustaining the law. ",
      "question": "What do we do if these principles are ever in conflect? When do we be like Daniel, and defy the king, and why do we be like Pres Woodruff, and submit to the law?",
      "response": "D&C 134 lays out the relationship between these two articles of faith is more detail. Neither principle is absolute. The government does indeed have the right to prohibit religious activities it finds dangerous, and every man deserves the freedom to believe and act according to their conscience. Every interaction here is a negotiation. \n\nOne might liken this question to a question of how to navigate activity in the church from within an unbelieving family. You may not be able to do absolutely everything you'd prefer, but you are still able to act according to what you think is right within your current situation. "
    }
  },
  "2025-12-12": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "his divine power hath given unto us all things that pertain unto life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue:",
      "hint": "2 Peter 1:3",
      "cipher": "SEWORBALUYNJZIHCMGQVXKFTDP"
    },
    "wordle": "WORTH",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Articles of Faith #13",
      "referenceText": "We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all men; inded, we may say that we follow the admonition of Paul-- We believe all things, we hope all things, we have endured many things, and hope to be able to endure all things. If there is anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after these things. ",
      "question": "What virtuous, lovely, of good report, or praiseworthy things have you sought out lately? ",
      "response": ""
    }
  },
  "2025-12-13": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Wherefore, it is lawful that he should have one wife, and they twain shall be one flesh, and all this that the earth might answer the end of its creation;",
      "hint": "D&C 49:16",
      "cipher": "LTHJVUPQFCSMYINGBZKRDOXAEW"
    },
    "wordle": "POINT",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "The Family Proclamation: P1",
      "referenceText": "We... solemnly proclaim that marriage between a man and a woman is ordained of God and that the family is central to the Creator's plan for the eternal destiny of His children.",
      "question": "In what sense is the family central to God's plan for us? How does that relate to Christ's role?",
      "response": "The entire point of the gospel is to learn how to build and participate in strong families. Christ's role in the plan is to show us how to treat one another, and how to work through the times when we need to forgive one another. The atonement ensures that we're able to maintain our position in God's eternal family."
    }
  },
  "2025-12-14": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "and we talk of christ, we rejoice in christ, we preach of christ, we prophesy of christ, and we write according to our prophecies, that our children may know to what source they may look for a remission of their sins.",
      "hint": "2 Nephi 25:26",
      "cipher": "MQLGCDVTZUSOEXBAYKNRJHIWFP"
    },
    "wordle": "FOUND",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "The Family Proclamation: P1",
      "referenceText": "Successful marriages and families are established and maintained on principles of faith, prayer, repentance, forgiveness, respect, love, compassion, work, and wholesome recreational activites.",
      "question": "Is there anything on this list we should be paying closer attention to?",
      "response": "The entire point of the gospel is to learn how to build and participate in strong families. Christ's role in the plan is to show us how to treat one another, and how to work through the times when we need to forgive one another. The atonement ensures that we're able to maintain our position in God's eternal family."
    }
  },
  "2025-12-24": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Now ye may suppose that this is foolishness in me; but behold I say unto you, that by small and simple things are great things brought to pass; and small means in many instances doth confound the wise.",
      "hint": "Alma 37:6",
      "cipher": "RPJOQLICFNHKSETBMWXAYDZVGU"
    },
    "wordle": "SMALL",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Luke 2:7",
      "referenceText": "And she brought forth her firstborn son, and wrapped him in swaddling clothes, and laid him in a manger; because there was no room for them in the inn",
      "question": "What can we learn from the symbol of the Christ being laid in a manger? ",
      "response": "Christmas is about new beginnings through Christ. We take the season of the year ending to look again at what we most want to be doing (the \"new star\" that we're trying to follow), and to take some new action, or recommit ourselves. It might be surprising that these new actions are most impactful when they come from \"small and simple\" things. Jumping immediately into strenuous activity is usually a recipe for failure. But \"small and simple\" is exactly how Christ was born. His birth was not clean or pristine. It was as messy as any other birth, and happened in a small, dirty place, surrounded by farm animals. \n\nSo don't be discouraged if your efforts are small, or if they don't seem to match your ambitions. Stay consistent and patient, and they will grow. "
    }
  },
  "2025-12-25": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "O, my beloved brethren, remember the awfulness in transgressing against that Holy God, and also the awfulness of yielding to the enticings of that cunning one. Remember, to be carnally-minded is death, and to be spiritually-minded is life eternal",
      "hint": "2 Nephi 9:39",
      "cipher": "SABLVYTZXCWIDFHJUKPNMQEORG"
    },
    "wordle": "SMILE",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "John 17:3",
      "referenceText": "And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent",
      "question": "How can we know Christ better?",
      "response": "The scryptogram scripture is my favorite answer to this. Be \"spiritually minded\". This means to see people as God sees them--with compassion, love and appreciation for their potential. It means to live in a way that allows the spirit to be with you--calm, and at peace. Not worried about the future or angry about the past. Christmas is about getting to know Christ better. It is easy to be \"carnally minded\" at a time where these so much to do, and so many material things around. But being spiritually minded will help us receive the gift of peace, and eternal life."
    }
  },
  "2025-12-26": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Therefore, hold up your light that it may shine unto the world. Behold I am the light which ye shall hold up—that which ye have seen me do.",
      "hint": "3 Nephi 18:24",
      "cipher": "DMFNJHKCYPTZBWROXELVISQAGU"
    },
    "wordle": "LIGHT",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "John 8:12",
      "referenceText": "Then spake Jesus again unto them, saying, I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life.",
      "question": "What does this mean?",
      "response": "Even in physics, there's a deep relationship between light and information. To walk in darkness means to walk without understanding of how things work. And to the extent that we walk without understanding, we're going to make mistakes. Christ's example shows us the right way to go. It doesn't show us the results of every other path, but it does show us the one that matters. "
    }
  },
  "2025-12-29": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And he shall sit as a refiner and purifier of silver: and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and purge them as gold and silver, that they may offer unto the Lord an offering in righteousness.",
      "hint": "Malachi 3:3",
      "cipher": "QZNECOFGVRLYHUXIBKPASMDJWT"
    },
    "wordle": "PURGE",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Exodus 19:5",
      "referenceText": "Now therefore, if ye will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then ye shall be a peculiar treasure unto me above all people: for all the earth is mine:",
      "question": "Why would God want to make a \"peculiar treasure\"? How might we become one?",
      "response": "A large part of the reason we're here is to be tested and refined, and the scriptures often use things like silver and gold to explain the process. Leaning into the process and actively working to become more like he wants us to be is difficult, but it literally makes us more valuable. We're of more service to our family and our neighbors, and God is able to put us to better and more effective use. "
    }
  },
  "2025-12-30": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And Jesus said unto them, I am the bread of life: he that cometh to me shall never hunger; and he that believeth on me shall never thirst.",
      "hint": "John 6:35",
      "cipher": "NSFOVZPCDQGAYXRUEWIJHTLBKM"
    },
    "wordle": "MANNA",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Exodus 16:4",
      "referenceText": "Then said the Lord unto Moses, Behold, I will rain bread from heaven for you; and the people shall go out and gather a certain rate every day, that I may prove them, whether they will walk in my law, or no.",
      "question": "What can the manna story teach us about Christ?",
      "response": "We are given a limited amount of resources every day. Physical, mental, emotional, spiritual, and temporal. How we choose to use them shows whether or not we're willing to keep the commandments. Like manna, we can't take more than what we need for today. How did you use your manna today? "
    }
  },
  "2026-01-05": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And Jesus answered and said unto him, Get thee behind me, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve.",
      "hint": "Luke 4:8",
      "cipher": "WRJSUQLNEIYHXDBGOAZFPCMTVK"
    },
    "wordle": "MODEL",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 1:12-13",
      "referenceText": "12 And it came to pass that when Moses had said these words, behold, Satan came tempting him, saying: Moses, son of man, worship me.\n\n13 And it came to pass that Moses looked upon Satan and said: Who art thou? For behold, I am a son of God, in the similitude of his Only Begotten; and where is thy glory, that I should worship thee?",
      "question": "What does it mean to worship something or someone? What's the difference between worshipping God and worshipping Satan?",
      "response": "God and Satan provide us with opposing patterns for how to accomplish things. God teaches us to forgive, to love, and to lead through persuasive example. Satan teaches us to control, to dominate, and to force at every opportunity. When we think about \"worshipping God\" we generally think about church and the temple, and when we think about \"worshipping Satan\", we generally think about occult rituals and things you might see in a horror movie, but worshipping is much more about which methodolgy you choose in your efforts. \n\nIn Norwegian, the verbs for \"to pray\" and \"to ask\" are the same word: \"å be\", and the word for \"worship\" is closely related: \"å tilbe\", or to \"pray to\". So, to worship means to pray to, or to make a request. We request blessings at the hand of Satan when we try to enact his plan, and we request blessings at the hand of God when we act with love and compassion. "
    }
  },
  "2026-01-06": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "He will swallow up death in victory; and the Lord God will wipe away tears from off all faces; and the rebuke of his people shall he take away from off all the earth: for the Lord hath spoken it.",
      "hint": "Isaiah 25:8",
      "cipher": "VHDYLKFOGXRZPUWEITCMSJNQBA"
    },
    "wordle": "EXALT",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 1:39",
      "referenceText": "For behold, this is my work and my glory—to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man.",
      "question": "What does the future hold for us?",
      "response": "The future holds the promise that if we are faithful and keep the covenants we've made, that there is no imagining the joy and peace that God has in store for us. But we do get a hint as we're able to stay in tune with the Spirit."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-07": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And he saith unto them, Why are ye fearful, O ye of little faith? Then he arose, and rebuked the winds and the sea; and there was a great calm.",
      "hint": "Matthew 8:26",
      "cipher": "VJXFYUKSBONRZTEIDHQPCMAGLW"
    },
    "wordle": "SCARE",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 1:20",
      "referenceText": "And it came to pass that Moses began to fear exceedingly; and as he began to fear, he saw the bitterness of hell. Nevertheless, calling upon God, he received strength, and he commanded, saying: Depart from me, Satan, for this one God only will I worship, which is the God of glory.",
      "question": "Why is fear associated with the bitterness of hell? How can we overcome fear?",
      "response": "Fear is anticipating a bad end. The wicked spend eternity expecting to be punished, waiting for something to go wrong, and always expecting things to get worse. Christ is a merciful judge to everyone who comes to him, but if you're afraid, you won't go, and you'll remain in self-inflicted torment. (This is the same as the story about the brass serpent.) \n\nIt's frequently said that the antidote to fear is faith. I think that's true, but for it to work faith can't just mean believing harder than our fear. Faith is about consistency, and doing the little things every time, even when you're not sure they're going to work. Faith brings us to Christ because what we learn about Christ lets us stop tormenting ourselves, and let him be our merciful judge. "
    }
  },
  "2025-12-31": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "18 Forasmuch as ye know that ye were not redeemed with corruptible things, as silver and gold, from your vain conversation received by tradition from your fathers; 19 But with the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish and without spot:",
      "hint": "1 Peter 1:18-19",
      "cipher": "XZVJIEDQFSTWLBRUYCPKGHMAON"
    },
    "wordle": "ALTAR",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Exodus 12:5",
      "referenceText": "Your lamb shall be without blemish, a male of the first year: ye shall take it out from the sheep, or from the goats",
      "question": "What is a sacrifice?",
      "response": "The root word of \"sacrifice\" is the word \"sacred\". We take something that is ordinary, and we make it sacred by turning it over to God. The children of Israel offered sacrifice of animals, and we offer sacrifices of time and of our hearts. In the Old Testatment, the sacrifices were to be young males without blemish, which points toward Christ as the sinless Son of God, crucified at a young age. It also points towards our own sacrifices of our intentions and ideals."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-01": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Behold, he was spoken of by Moses; yea, and behold a type was raised up in the wilderness, that whosoever would look upon it might live. And many did look and live.",
      "hint": "Alma 33:19",
      "cipher": "BEXROZYCPLIFVHJUNAQDKMSGTW"
    },
    "wordle": "BRASS",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Number 21:8-9",
      "referenceText": "8 And the Lord said unto Moses, Make thee a fiery serpent, and set it upon a pole: and it shall come to pass, that every one that is bitten, when he looketh upon it, shall live.\n9 And Moses made a serpent of brass, and put it upon a pole, and it came to pass, that if a serpent had bitten any man, when he beheld the serpent of brass, he lived.",
      "question": "How is the brass serpent like Christ?",
      "response": "We have to look to Christ to be healed. Christ was lifted on the cross like the serpent was lifted on a rod. Christ gives us victory over the original serpent, Satan. We have to confront our sins, we cannot hide from them and expect the bad effects to just go away on their own. "
    }
  },
  "2026-01-02": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "For as Jonas was three days and three nights in the whale’s belly; so shall the Son of man be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth.",
      "hint": "Matthew 12:40",
      "cipher": "TMKCVOZAFBPYNDULHSIXWEGQRJ"
    },
    "wordle": "THREE",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Jonah 1:17",
      "referenceText": "Now the Lord had prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah. And Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights.",
      "question": "Christ referred to his time in the tomb as \"the sign of Jonah\". How was Jonah's experience like Christ's? Do we ever have similar experiences?",
      "response": "The sign of Jonah that Christ spoke about was specifically relating to the period of 3 days that he was in the tomb. There were a period of darkness and despair for Jonah, until the whale vomited him back up, but he went forth from the whale ready to do what God had asked him to do. Christ rose from the grave glorified, and when we are in the dark periods of our own lives, we can commune with God, waiting until the time has come for us to be delivered out of that darkness, so that we can go forth with renewed commitment."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-12": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "5 For thou hast made him a little lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and honor. 6 Thou madest him to have dominion over the works of thy hands; thou hast put all things under his feet:",
      "hint": "Psalms 8:5-6",
      "cipher": "ROFQYWPGSXCTAIJDHLVBMKENZU"
    },
    "wordle": "EARTH",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 2:1",
      "referenceText": "I am the Beginning and the End, the Almighty God; by mine Only Begotten I created these things; yea, in the beginning I created the heaven, and the earth upon which thou standest.",
      "question": "What can we learn from the creation of the earth?",
      "response": "In the temple, we go through the creation story, and there we see Adam participating with Christ in the creation of the earth. In the temple, Adam represents all of us, and each day, we create our own worlds. God gives commandments, and hand in hand with Christ, we strive to shape our realities according to those commandments. As we do this, we'll be able to look at our lives, and with our Father, say: \"It is good.\""
    }
  },
  "2026-01-13": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "1 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. 2 The same was in the beginning with God. 3 All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made that was made.",
      "hint": "John 1:1-3",
      "cipher": "BAUCMSXKLZONGHFDPWRJQIYVET"
    },
    "wordle": "DRAFT",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 3:5",
      "referenceText": "5 And every plant of the field before it was in the earth, and every herb of the field before it grew. For I, the Lord God, created all things, of which I have spoken, spiritually, before they were naturally upon the face of the earth. For I, the Lord God, had not caused it to rain upon the face of the earth. And I, the Lord God, had created all the children of men; and not yet a man to till the ground; for in heaven created I them; and there was not yet flesh upon the earth, neither in the water, neither in the air;",
      "question": "What might it mean to create something spiritually? What does that have to do with us participating with God in creating our own lives?",
      "response": "Creating something spiritually means both planning for something, and also creating the circumstances were you can turn it into a reality. Mom and I created this family spiritually before we created it physically. We did this by preparing and getting married in the temple, by learning to provide for our children, and by raising you in a way that helped you turn into the wonderful people you are. We are still creating, both phyically and spiritually. You can begin creating your life spiritually by planning and preparing now for the kind of life you want to have in the future."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-14": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Now the Lord had shown unto me, Abraham, the intelligences that were organized before the world was; and among all these there were many of the noble and great ones;",
      "hint": "Abraham 3:22",
      "cipher": "HLZPUAYKEIFSQXNOWGTDMRCJBV"
    },
    "wordle": "IMAGE",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Abraham 4:26",
      "referenceText": "And the Gods took counsel among themselves and said: Let us go down and form man in our image, after our likeness; and we will give them dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.",
      "question": "Why does this scripture refer to multiple Gods, instead of just one?",
      "response": "We have 3 different versions of the creation story in the scriptures. 1 in Genesis, 1 in Moses, and 1 in Abraham. There is one more version in the temple. They are all very similar to each other, but they each have differences. One difference in the temple version is that while Heavenly Father is directing, it is Christ, working together with Adam, (who we're told in the temple represents all of us) who does the actual work. \n\nGod showed Abraham the spirits that existed before the world was created, and said that there were many \"noble and great ones\". Hopefully we are among that number. We are children of God--what does that make us?"
    }
  },
  "2026-01-15": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "For behold, this is my work and my glory—to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man.",
      "hint": "Moses 1:39",
      "cipher": "CNAIGKVMFHEJWUQTZLXDPYSOBR"
    },
    "wordle": "FRUIT",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Genesis 1:28",
      "referenceText": "And God blessed them, and God said unto them, Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth, and subdue it: and have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over every living thing that moveth upon the earth.",
      "question": "Is our only purpose to make more people?",
      "response": "What is God's purpose? Is it just to have children, endlessly? No. They're vitally important, but our purpose is to replenish and subdue the earth, and to rule over it wisely. If we want to do that for more than a single generation, children are needed, but more important is that our purpose is not to make MORE people, it's to make BETTER people. Just like God's purpose is to help us reach our potential, your purpose is to reach your, and to help others reach theirs. I am LOVING watching you guys grow into yours, and doing that helps me fulfill mine. "
    }
  },
  "2026-01-16": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And then shall it come to pass, that the spirits of those who are righteous are received into a state of happiness, which is called paradise, a state of rest, a state of peace, where they shall rest from all their troubles and from all care, and sorrow.",
      "hint": "Alma 40:12",
      "cipher": "WZXFYITKQDHRNPSEGUBJMOVCLA"
    },
    "wordle": "SEVEN",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Genesis 2:2-3",
      "referenceText": "2 And on the seventh day God ended his work which he had made; and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made.\n3 And God blessed the seventh day, and sanctified it: because that in it he had rested from all his work which God created and made.",
      "question": "What makes the Sabbath \"Blessed\" to you?",
      "response": ""
    }
  },
  "2026-01-19": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And when he saw a fig tree in the way, he came to it, and found nothing thereon, but leaves only, and said unto it, Let no fruit grow on thee henceforward for ever. And presently the fig tree withered away.",
      "hint": "Matthew 21:19",
      "cipher": "RAHFZEDITQUJNSMOXBYWCKVLGP"
    },
    "wordle": "COVER",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Genesis 3:7",
      "referenceText": "And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked; and they sewed fig leaves together, and made themselves aprons",
      "question": "The term \"apply a fig leaf\" is sometimes used for when someone tries to make something that's obviously bad look just barely ok. Adam and Eve used their \"fig leaves\" to hide from God. Do we have any \"fig leaves\", that we use to try to hide our sins or try to make up for deficiencies in other areas? ",
      "response": "We definitely all try to do this in some way. And the lesson of the Garden of Eden is that God already knows everything about us, including the bad stuff. Trying to hide it from him just looks silly. When we confess though, we're able to make covenants that help us know how to obtain forgiveness."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-20": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And when thou prayest, thou shalt not be as the hypocrites are: for they love to pray standing in the synagogues and in the corners of the streets, that they may be seen of men. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward.",
      "hint": "Matthew 6:5",
      "cipher": ""
    },
    "wordle": "FLOCK",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 5:20-21",
      "referenceText": "20 And Abel, he also brought of the firstlings of his flock, and of the fat thereof. And the Lord had respect unto Abel, and to his offering;\n21 But unto Cain, and to his offering, he had not respect. Now Satan knew this, and it pleased him. And Cain was very wroth, and his countenance fell.",
      "question": "Why did the Lord reject Cain's offering, but not Abel's?",
      "response": "One key to understanding this story is in verse 18: And Cain loved Satan more than God. And Satan commanded him, saying: Make an offering unto the Lord. \n Sometimes we do good things for the wrong reasons. Sometimes God can use those actions to change our motivations, but until our motives become pure, we will not receive the true blessings we're looking for.\n\nLater in this chapter it talks about offering an acceptable sacrifice, which today means offering our whole hearts."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-21": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And my people must needs be chastened until they learn obedience, if it must needs be, by the things which they suffer.",
      "hint": "D&C 105:9",
      "cipher": ""
    },
    "wordle": "CHAOS",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Genesis 3:16",
      "referenceText": "16 Unto the woman he said, I will greatly multiply thy sorrow and thy conception; in sorrow thou shalt bring forth children; and thy desire shall be to thy husband, and he shall rule over thee.",
      "question": "Is a woman's only purpose to make babies and be ruled by her husband?",
      "response": "The story of Adam and Eve is DEEPLY symbolic. This isn't the standard take, but it's one I'm comfortable giving as an answer to a very good question. \n\nTake Eve as symbolic of the impulse to try new things, explore, and learn. She dives into the world of chaos, and brings down the world of paradise with her. Take Adam as the one who follows the rules. When things get a bit out of control, he's the one who establishes order and control again. Now, consider that you have an \"Adam\" and an \"Eve\" inside of you. If Adam were in control, nothing would ever change and no growth would ever occur. If Eve were in control, we'd descend into chaos with no hope of ever climbing back out. Eve is the one who brings about new things, and those new things almost always involve struggle. \"I will greatly multiply thy sorrow and thy conception\". And when that happens, we instinctively try to make sense of the new world we find ourselves in. \"thy desire shall be to thy husband, and he shall rule over thee.\" \n\nRather than reading this as a reinforcement of gender roles, take it as a window into your own psyche. "
    }
  },
  "2026-01-24": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "He hath given unto you that ye might know good from evil, and he hath given unto you that ye might choose life or death; and ye can do good and be restored unto that which is good, or have that which is good restored unto you; or ye can do evil, and have that which is evil restored unto you.",
      "hint": "Helaman 14:31",
      "cipher": "IRMPFGSXDOTJBZLWEAYVCUQKHN"
    },
    "wordle": "APPLE",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Genesis 3:4-6",
      "referenceText": "4 And the serpent said unto the woman, Ye shall not surely die:\n5 For God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall be as gods, knowing good and evil.\n6 And when the woman saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleasant to the eyes, and a tree to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave also unto her husband with her; and he did eat.",
      "question": "What is a \"fruit\"? What are the fruits of knowing good and evil?",
      "response": "In a scriptural context, a fruit is a consequence.So, what are the consequences of knowing good and evil? The consequence is that you are now accountable for your actions. If you do something wrong before you know that it's wrong, you're innocent, just like Adam and Eve were in the Garden. BUT, if you don't know what's wrong, you also don't know what's right, and just like you can't be blamed for anything wrong, you also can't grow."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-25": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "13 For thou hast said in thine heart, I will ascend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the stars of God: I will sit also upon the mount of the congregation, in the sides of the north:14 I will ascend above the heights of the clouds; I will be like the most High.",
      "hint": "Isaiah 14:13-14",
      "cipher": "OYGCBMPTWFVHJLZQKARIXESNDU"
    },
    "wordle": "AGENT",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 4:3",
      "referenceText": "Wherefore, because that Satan rebelled against me, and sought to destroy the agency of man, which I, the Lord God, had given him, and also, that I should give unto him mine own power; by the power of mine Only Begotten, I caused that he should be cast down;",
      "question": "How does Satan still seek to destroy our agency?",
      "response": "In order to truly exercise agency, you need 4 things:\n1. A correct understanding of what your choices will get you.\n 2. Some emotional stake in the outcome. If you don't care what happens, you are not acting as an agent.\n 3. A true choice--if you're being presented with a false choice, you don't truly have any agency.\n4. The ability to change. (ie, to do something different this time than you did last time.\n\nIf that's true, then how might Satan try to destroy agency?\n1. He confuses and hides the consequences of right and wrong, generally by taking advantage of the fact that some consequences are immediate and others are delayed.\n2. He ncourages apathy in the face of complexity or challenge.\n3. He will try to convince us that all roads lead us to the same place, or that nothing we do will matter.\n4. He denies the prospect of change."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-26": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "3 Lo, children are an heritage of the Lord: and the fruit of the womb is his reward. 4 As arrows are in the hand of a mighty man; so are children of the youth. 5 Happy is the man that hath his quiver full of them: they shall not be ashamed, but they shall speak with the enemies in the gate.",
      "hint": "Psalms 127:3-5",
      "cipher": "VWTQODAPLKYGZMFXEBJICHNRSU"
    },
    "wordle": "SLAIN",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 6:2",
      "referenceText": "2 And Adam knew his wife again, and she bare a son, and he called his name Seth. And Adam glorified the name of God; for he said: God hath appointed me another seed, instead of Abel, whom Cain slew.",
      "question": "Why was Adam excited, while his son had been killed?",
      "response": "Adam was definitely NOT excited that Abel had been killed. Abel represented the thing that Adam wanted most of all: righteous children. But Adam was glad that Seth WAS righteous, and that Seth taught HIS children to be righteous. The thing that I want most as a parent, is your YOU to teach YOUR children how to be righteous and happy."
    }
  },
  "2026-01-27": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Wherefore, we shall have a perfect knowledge of all our guilt, and our uncleanness, and our nakedness; and the righteous shall have a perfect knowledge of their enjoyment, and their righteousness, being clothed with purity, yea, even with the robe of righteousness.",
      "hint": "2 Ne 9:14",
      "cipher": "REKPHVQTLZBNFXGCWJIYMASDOU"
    },
    "wordle": "CLEAN",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 6:57",
      "referenceText": "Wherefore teach it unto your children, that all men, everywhere, must repent, or they can in nowise inherit the kingdom of God, for no unclean thing can dwell there, or dwell in his presence; for, in the language of Adam, Man of Holiness is his name, and the name of his Only Begotten is the Son of Man, even Jesus Christ, a righteous Judge, who shall come in the meridian of time.",
      "question": "What counts as \"unclean\"?",
      "response": "We've probably all been on the receiving end of someone ruining a moment. I think that gets at the idea of being \"unclean\", particularly in God's eyes. We're trying to build lives of peace and prosperity, reverence, and love for God and each other. When something comes to disrupt those feelings, it feels like a stain that we have to remove. "
    }
  },
  "2026-01-28": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Therefore we are buried with him by baptism into death: that like as Christ was raised up from the dead by the glory of the Father, even so we also should walk in newness of life.",
      "hint": "Romans 6:4",
      "cipher": "QFHBKANMUZLDVIPRWYCXJOETSG"
    },
    "wordle": "QUICK",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 6:65",
      "referenceText": "And thus he was baptized, and the Spirit of God descended upon him, and thus he was born of the Spirit, and became quickened in the inner man.",
      "question": "What does it mean to be \"quickened in the inner man\"?",
      "response": "To be quickened means to become alive. The inner man is the spiritual man, as opposed to the natural man. Adam's baptism, of water and the spirit brought him to life spiritually. "
    }
  },
  "2026-02-02": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "But now mine own eyes have beheld God; but not my natural, but my spiritual eyes, for my natural eyes could not have beheld; for I should have withered and died in his presence;",
      "hint": "Moses 1:11",
      "cipher": "NDWZKPBJYELUHGFSVQRMXAITCO"
    },
    "wordle": "STOOD",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 7:4",
      "referenceText": "And I saw the Lord; and he stood before my face, and he talked with me, even as a man talketh one with another, face to face; and he said unto me: Look, and I will show unto thee the world for the space of many generations.",
      "question": "Why does the Lord show himself in different forms?",
      "response": "The scriptures are pretty clear that when anyone receives the privilege of seeing God, it happens with \"spiritual eyes\" rather than \"natural ones\". I can't say exactly how that changes the rules of perception, but I'm sure that it does. My guess is that God shows us what we need to understand. "
    }
  },
  "2026-02-03": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Rest in the Lord, and wait patiently for him: fret not thyself because of him who prospereth in his way, because of the man who bringeth wicked devices to pass",
      "hint": "Psalm 37:7",
      "cipher": "SYOHZWXEUFCKABRVTDINGQPJML"
    },
    "wordle": "TIRED",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 7:58, 61",
      "referenceText": "58 And again Enoch wept and cried unto the Lord, saying: When shall the earth rest?\n61 And the day shall come that the earth shall rest, but before that day the heavens shall be darkened, and a veil of darkness shall cover the earth; and the heavens shall shake, and also the earth; and great tribulations shall be among the children of men, but my people will I preserve",
      "question": "When does rest come? ",
      "response": "A lot of times we want rest to come immediately. But God was teaching Enoch that that's not actually the way things work. The dark times still need to be passed through. We can't just skip over them. But, the promise to the righteous is the God is with us even during the dark times, and that hope and faith will get us through to the peaceful rest."
    }
  },
  "2026-02-04": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "I will send my fear before thee, and will destroy all the people to whom thou shalt come, and I will make all thine enemies turn their backs unto thee.",
      "hint": "Exodus 23:27",
      "cipher": "UFICVGMDHWTKXYQZJPLOEBSRNA"
    },
    "wordle": "LOVED",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 7:16-17",
      "referenceText": "16 And from that time forth there were wars and bloodshed among them; but the Lord came and dwelt with his people, and they dwelt in righteousness.\n17 The fear of the Lord was upon all nations, so great was the glory of the Lord, which was upon his people. And the Lord blessed the land, and they were blessed upon the mountains, and upon the high places, and did flourish.",
      "question": "If the people \"dwelt in righteousness\" they why was the Lord feared instead of loved?",
      "response": "In this verse specifically, the ones that feared God were the OTHER nations, not Enoch's rightous city. There are plenty of places in the scriptures though where \"fear\" means \"respect\". We'll read a lot of places where we're commanded to \"fear the Lord\", and these are really instructions to respect God and the commandments we receive. "
    }
  },
  "2026-02-05": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "Now this is the state of the souls of the wicked, yea, in darkness, and a state of awful, fearful looking for the fiery indignation of the wrath of God upon them; thus they remain in this state, as well as the righteous in paradise, until the time of their resurrection.",
      "hint": "Alma 40:14",
      "cipher": "QLZXTIDCKFPVNUJWHBAMYOESGR"
    },
    "wordle": "WRATH",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 7:1",
      "referenceText": "And it came to pass that Enoch continued his speech, saying: Behold, our father Adam taught these things, and many have believed and become the sons of God, and many have believed not, and have perished in their sins, and are looking forth with fear, in torment, for the fiery indignation of the wrath of God to be poured out upon them.",
      "question": "Why will the sinners perish/not be forgiven?",
      "response": "Enoch is talking about the atonement, and that Christ will forgive everyone who comes and sincerely repents. All paths to forgivness lead through Christ, and if people will not come to him, they remain spiritually stuck where they are until they realize that there is peace available to them. "
    }
  },
  "2026-02-06": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And behold, they were encircled about as if it were by fire; and it came down from heaven, and the multitude did witness it, and did bear record; and angels did come down out of heaven and did minister unto them.",
      "hint": "3 Nephi 19:14",
      "cipher": "VZHCDPIYELWRQUXATNKJFBGMOS"
    },
    "wordle": "CLOTH",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 7:3-4",
      "referenceText": "3 And it came to pass that I turned and went up on the mount; and as I stood upon the mount, I beheld the heavens open, and I was clothed upon with glory;\n4 And I saw the Lord; and he stood before my face, and he talked with me, even as a man talketh one with another, face to face; and he said unto me: Look, and I will show unto thee the world for the space of many generations.",
      "question": "What does it mean to be \"clothed up with glory\"?",
      "response": "Being \"clothed with glory\" is mentioned a lot in the scriptures, especially when someone is being prepared to meet God. Other times it's described as being surrounded by fire, which I think is a metaphor for brightness, energy, and power beyond our usual ability to describe. In the temple, we wear special white robes over our clothes that represent being clothed with glory. \n\nGlory is how we'll be ressurrected, and it's a restoration of all the good things we've tried to be and do in our life. Being clothed with glory is getting a taste of what the celestial kingdom will be like, so that you can have a celestial experience here."
    }
  },
  "2026-02-07": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "And the multitude of them that believed were of one heart and of one soul: neither said any of them that ought of the things which he possessed was his own; but they had all things common.",
      "hint": "Acts 4:32",
      "cipher": "FKUIMVZNCXHWEPQSTYRLBOADJG"
    },
    "wordle": "DWELT",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Moses 7:18",
      "referenceText": "18 And the Lord called his people Zion, because they were of one heart and one mind, and dwelt in righteousness; and there was no poor among them.",
      "question": "How is Zion different from the rest of the world?",
      "response": "Zion is different becuase instead of fighting with each other, with everyone competing to be the best, they work together, and look after one another. Instead of arguing to convince someone that they're right, people in Zion listen to each other and try to understand each other. They share easily, and always work to include people in righteousness."
    }
  },
  "2026-02-09": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "let virtue garnish their thoughts unceasingly; then shall thy confidence wax strong in the presence of God; and the doctrine of the priesthood shall distill on thy soul as the dews from heaven.",
      "hint": "D&C 121:45",
      "cipher": "PTAJBMDCLXWRSUFYKOGZIQNVHE"
    },
    "wordle": "THINK",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Gen 6:5",
      "referenceText": "And God saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually.",
      "question": "When we imagine, what do we imagine? ",
      "response": "How great would it be, if instead of getting caught up in thoughts that are angry, frustrated, selfish, or lazy, our thoughts were consumed with imagining ways to serve, or imagining ways to become the people we really want to be? This would be an example of virtue garnishing my thoughts unceaseingly. We should actively try to imagine good things."
    }
  },
  "2026-02-10": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "and after Alma had said these words, both alma and helam were buried in the water; and they arose and came forth out of the water rejoicing, being filled with the spirit",
      "hint": "Mosiah 18:14",
      "cipher": "JFDABCENRUTYZPXQSKIOVLHGMW"
    },
    "wordle": "WATER",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Gen 6:17-18",
      "referenceText": "And behold, I, even I, do bring a flood of waters upon the earth, to destroy all flesh, wherein is the breath of life, from under heaven; and every thing that is in the earth shall die. \n\nBut with thee will I establish my covenant; and thou shalt come into the ark, thou and thy sons, and they wife, and thy sons' wives with thee. ",
      "question": "How is the flood like baptism?",
      "response": "The earth was covered with water, just like we are when we're baptised. Also, the world was sinful, just like us when we're baptised. God established his covenant with Noah, just like he does with us. And when we keep that covenant, we help save our families and all the other good things in our lives. "
    }
  },
  "2026-02-11": {
    "scryptogram": {
      "solution": "and their mourning was turned into joy, and their lamentations into the praise and thanksgiving unto the lord jesus christ, their redeemer",
      "hint": "3 Ne 10:10",
      "cipher": "VRNMTQYJWKHUPXBOIALZEGSDFC"
    },
    "wordle": "ALIVE",
    "prompt": {
      "reference": "Gen 6:19",
      "referenceText": "And of every living thing of all flesh, two of every sort shalt thou bring into the ark, to keep them alive with thee; they shall be male and female",
      "question": "Why did God have Noah save the animals, rather than just save them Himself? Is there anything we can learn from that?",
      "response": "One thing I learn from that is that even when it feels like my whole world is going wrong, I have a responsibility to find and protect the good things that God has given me. And even when everything feels bad, that's still a LOT of things. Enough to fill an enormous ark."
    }
  }
}